hey everyone it is
October 21st 2022 we're in cohort one
the textbook group it's meeting 21
and we're having our first discussion on
chapter nine
chapter nine is model based data
analysis let's look at what the section
headers are
there's a short introduction
a discussion of meta Bayesian methods
which is going to be very interesting
and in some ways is even like an entry
point
to thinking about
entity modeling in active inference
and so that'll be kind of fun
we'll return to variational Applause
resonating with our
just completed discussion on chapter
four and LaPlace
then
section 9.4 9.5
are going to help us see where data
in terms of like gigabytes of actual
good day Jacob
actual data from measurements and so on
where these come into play with models
so how does one go from a um furnished
trainable model
to a parameterized specified model which
actually
is explaining variance in real world
data sets
and then there's some examples of GMS
and some models of false inference
um well
I added only one General
question
from
um a lighter reading
I think as we all hear
move through this we can generate a lot
of other key points and questions
um
ultimately the models described in this
book are only useful if they can answer
scientific questions
but just we could
rehearse the introduction again but
let's just go
Um into it so metabasian methods
this chapter deals with utility of
active inference formulations and
analyzing data from behavioral
experiments
so one could imagine all kinds of
bodily verbal
digital
Behavior
this goes beyond proof of principle
simulations we've seen in previous
chapters and instead
exploits active inference in answering
scientific questions
broadly speaking there's two related
reasons for fitting a computational
model to observe Behavior
the first is to estimate parameters of
Interest
the second is to compare alternative
hypotheses
so to parameterize
from data
is one opportunity
that is to
um
make some model of brain function and
then
um
understand within one person or one
group or two groups
how
um
you can consider those parameterizations
to be phenotypes
phenotype is something of a biological
organism or system that's measurable so
like femur length is a phenotype
but also a phenotype doesn't have to
just be something that's measurable on
the body with a ruler like phenotype
might be distance ran in the first 50
seconds after the hawk flies through the
sky on a cloudy day
and so then that is still a measurement
that could be inferred or discussed or
made
and we're talking about computational
phenotyping because the data and
observations for sure are like a basal
phenotype
like the button being clicked was
um
measurable pheno means to show
but also we could talk about like the
Precision variables in our cognitive
model as being phenotypic
and also model comparison
can be used
so whereas this first modality of
parameterization is like the data set is
fixed we collected 240 fmri data sets
now we're going to parameterize so we're
going to give some
um plasticity to our model and we're
going to fit parameters so that so that
our model is like the best resembling it
can to these 240 fmri data sets we have
in the second modality
we're treating in some ways the models
as fixed
and then evaluating
to what extent
different models
Stack Up
and that can be used at a very fine
scale
to look for different models that fit
better to a given data set
but also this is where we
can talk about like
actual biological explanations and
predictions so like to give an example
from yes please Ali first
uh sorry a related question to this
whole discussion is uh I think it was in
section 9.2 uh it says this goes beyond
the proof of principle simulations we've
seen in previous chapters and instead
exploits active inference and answering
scientific questions uh I didn't quite
understand this statement here because
uh
in the previous chapters uh we were we
were also engaged with modeling uh the
real scientific phenomena right so what
does proof of principle simulation here
exactly mean and how does it uh differ
from the approach uh I mean from
answering a real scientific questions
yeah good question
does anyone want to give a thought or I
can give a thought too
um
I mean literally just these following
that the first and second reasons to use
um
active inference in this way it's like
instead of just modeling something
and saying oh that looks like
what what we intended the model or oh
gosh it looks really predictive or
whatever
getting more rigorous with it to
specifically
you know enumerate parameters for a
particular model
right
and and then compare multiple models
like trying to say
which one is you know uh
more precise that's that's a different
thing than what has was being done in
the book previously like we're just
building up the model and seeing how it
kind of worked before and now we're like
talking about putting it into a like a
Machinery that's going to you know uh
select on models like which ones best
fit or whatever
well said I I totally agree
um preview although arguably like the
chapter five neurobiology the tables of
examples were answering scientific
questions but those generative models
were not largely presented but in the
papers
one could have gone in but yes the
previous generative models were like
built from the ground up
and then like oh look at this
interesting Behavior
now we're building the Machinery to take
in
real data
and fit that
and then there's the the two uses
of parameterization or the two uses of
data fitting
to find the best parameters for a given
data set and model
and also to compare models
model comparison
all right
now we get to the very excellent figure
is the meta Bayesian inference
what does anyone see in this figure
Ali
well as pointed out in the text uh the
inner box
somehow represents the generative model
of the phenomena we're trying to we're
observing but the outer dashed box is
somehow our generative model as The
Observers so the term metabasian I think
used here to denote this kind of change
of perspective to higher uh to a higher
level of viewpoint uh I mean
to add another layer of hierarchy to the
already hierarchical generative models
we had before
yeah great well said and this out so we
we could have had an arbitrarily nested
um well just to make a simple point this
is the discrete time formulation pomdp
figure 4.3
and that can be nested in an arbitrary
way and composed
and meta Bayesian is like putting
the wrapping paper on the gift because
this outermost layer is us
Brock
um
so the last time this came up was uh in
the context I think it was in the other
cohort but we were talking about
um
the you know provenance of the model the
the impetus for it being
um
you know as a tool for
uh diagnosis of patients for you know
non-typical sort of neuro um so
uh I'm I guess I'm curious maybe uh if
there's a simple way to understand it
from that perspective but I also have um
a
another question I guess which is
If This Is Us modeling
it seems like it would be like infinite
really recursive because every time you
add another layer like then there's
another layer that's not being modeled
of how we're actually modeling it and
therefore we would have to but then if
we
account for that then
then there would be another outer uh you
know I don't know if that's just uh
infinite regression towards the hidden
state
one or the other or but um
or I'm just that's nonsense but
yeah no no it's it's not I think
let's let's
talk about the uh setting of the
clinical neuroimaging
so
the inner model is going to be the
cognitive behavioral model of the
patient just speaking of this the
participant the recipient of action as
the patient they're selecting green or
blue coins or whatever they're doing
some behavioral Paradigm isocating or
choice or decision making
we're modeling their action perception
attention and so on
whether we
formalize it or not
the experimenter's behavior is
influencing
the parameterization of the patients
like
we are choosing populations
and sampling patients
here is like the parameterization of the
experiment
we'll have 20 people they'll come in for
two sessions we're gonna do 11
um you know of this
and here's like the data coming out of
so this o here
is the observation that the patient sees
and their inference on what they're
seeing
experimental stimuli are actually an
action from the experimenter
we're pushing the o to their screen so
this o tilde is their o sequence
we're getting
data from the experiment
we could choose to
be ignorant or implicit
about our parameterization
or maybe even this is a nested model
we made a governance decision in the lab
to decide who gets to decide this
and the constraints were the cost and
the availability
nested
modeling of the Outer Loop
and what about infinite recursion
and I think
one silver lining or Saving Grace or
whatever or just strength of the
Bayesian graph or active inference
framework
is
we know we can always
Dive In
and like build from a node or we can
just treat the edges of our base graph
as like a Markov blanket with the
unknown
so we could say we made a simple model
of decision making here
and then we could this could be a
multi-agent simulation and each of those
could have another nested model
and then we could get it fixed then
maybe it's irrelevant
or maybe we want to know anyways but
what good will it I don't know yeah or
it doesn't fit and we do want to know or
yeah let's just say that the the
pragmatic value for us is um
High statistical power and sensitivity
for a diagnosis of a um
neuro condition
so like
we want the inner loop
to be in the point we don't want to be
like spending money Beyond diminishing
returns on our experiment
we want to actually like diagnose and
help the people in this limited
situation
um
then one could do model comparison
with just I'm ignoring all of this I'm
just going to parameterize just just I'm
going to call it like I see it
then one could have another but but if
one were to engage in a research program
where we we collected one data set
then yeah let's just call like we see it
but now we have the opportunity to
design a second cohort of fmri
experiments
should we do two people for a hundred
sessions or a hundred people for two
sessions who should those hundred people
be
so at that point having a policy
selection
outer loop enabling
seems pretty relevant
now we could make that
um simple maybe it's we always pick 30
participants
maybe it's we either do a small
experiment with three or we do a big one
with 30. it's just simpler those are the
two Pathways we have
or maybe it's a
you know
Etc but then you could do model
comparison and evaluation
on those increasingly complex outer loop
models
none of that
would be influencing
the structure of the cognitive model of
the patient
so
for all you block friends heads in the
chat
one could imagine that there's
um
human fmri cognitive model
this is a versionable cognitive model
open source
and then different lab groups could have
open or closed models with open or
closed data
around their decision making about how
they're using
a core model
this is also just a on a more um
qualitative point and then Ali like this
is where we can start to talk about
moving beyond implicit biases
not just like perch implicit biases or
anything like that it's just like we're
doing investigation and exploration
we're externalizing and exteriorizing
our priors
and we're working such that the relevant
features
that are in the Box
are all externalized in terms of the
scientific apparatuses parameterization
and that's at least something where we
can move towards and someone could say
well you haven't made your hyper hyper
hyper priors explicit
but isn't that a better conversation to
have than
you didn't say why you chose this many
people for the experiment
it could be like you didn't State The
Meta governance
of how you came to the decision to do 30
participants
I mean it makes it it sounds like it
makes it really a lot easier to think
about comparing and Counting showing
that you accounted for your methods um
like it's the same you're doing the
exact same experiment right
um might be able to move the needle a
little bit on some of the reproducible
Earth
replication crisis things like
in that vein yeah great point
um
Ollie
I don't see what uh Rock just mentions
um as a side note uh I think
approaching this
um kind of I mean this approach to uh
model based or uh better the
marble-based data analysis
takes the
infinitism stance as an implicit uh
somehow the philosophical stance because
uh if we don't think in terms of
infinitism
I don't think we were able to
model adequately these kind of
metabasian reasoning because we'll get
at some point to as Brock said just
infinite regressive reasons so at least
in my opinion it's somehow implicitly
takes the infinitism stance here
as uh proposed by Peter Klein
at least in large part because as
infinitism uh stands claims will need
somehow the subjectively and objectively
available
reasons to uh to to model or to
construct or Justify true beliefs in
other words the reason must be uh
non-repeating and infinitely available
to us in order for us to be able to
construct that true belief so I'm not
quite sure about it but it looks very
similar to infinitism stance
yeah interesting
um introduction wasn't
familiar with this area
um like
approximate Bayesian computation bounded
rationality
the composability of Base graphs
these are
we get to eat our slice of cake
and recognize that there is the rest of
the cake and the table and the world
outside of the restaurant
and so on like we can just say the the
GM that we made was the thermometer and
a temperature value
and someone can say but what about
humidity and it's like there's a
composability
but
um
we're not within the positivist or the
falsificationist
like well my model of temperature and
thermometer
is positive evidence that that's all
that's happening or it's the best model
we have we're just waiting for it to be
disproven
we can have like a Bayesian portfolio
of models and all of them
can be understood as um Maps
as composable Maps
um
could this lead to
Bayes optimal experimental design
of research programs
like statistical power the the famous
statistics quotation is like something
about an autopsy like the statistician
is not going to diagnose it it's they
come in and they tell you what went
wrong with the autopsy but that's also
that's not fundamental to statistics
that's actually just a little bit of
like a joke about the practice of
research which is like the
biostatistician just being from my own
research experience they're called in
for assistance on a complex already
collected data set
and so it's like well we had three mice
in March and then we had six mice in
April
how do we balance this
versus The Upfront
conversation to help design a high
statistical power experiment
and so like
statistics up front
it's gonna increase the reproducibility
and alignability of experiments
it is a sanity check if not a formal
verification that the experiment is
going to tell you something
and it allows for um replicating
experiments selecting experiments
based upon like their statistical power
okay
following sections unpack an example of
generic inference that may be used for
metabasing inference the variational
LaPlace with hierarchical models
then there's going to be a simple recipe
that's related to the uh one of the
other questions up here
okay
variational LaPlace
may be used for more generic likelihood
functions than those encountered earlier
which were defined as gaussian so
previously
the family of functions that we are
doing variational inference with was
gaussians
now
we can generalize Beyond using only
gaussian distributions
by saying whatever it is
we're going to do a laplacian
approximation
so even if it's like a something very
strange and as mentioned in um cohort 2
discussion just an hour ago
the LaPlace approximation has two
parameters the the mode the center of
the bell and just the width of the
parabola
it's guaranteed to capture some of the
variants of the distribution for
distributions with a central tendency
gaussian or otherwise it can do well
for distributions that are like
multimodal
it does not do well because it gets
tricked to finding the mode which may
only capture like a minority of the
overall bulk and again the SPM textbook
lays out side by side
LaPlace variational Bays non-parametric
sampling approaches
from those laplacian approximations
we're going to do variational inference
so
the real distribution might be
unfactorizable or not we don't know what
family of functions it even is
but we know that the LaPlace
approximations that we make on those
distributions for sure will be amenable
to variational inference
and because of the quadratic nature
we can do gradient Ascent so just like
the ball going to the bottom of the bowl
this is just an inverted Parabola so
it's just gradient asense on the
mountain
all right
parametric empirical base
um
this
usage
of a matrix to represent the
experimental layout
is heavily used in SPM
this is looking a lot like a regression
this is actually a little bit of a short
section 9.4
[Music]
um
this part here
comparing the evidence for a model
where the second element is allowed to
deviate from zero
or the precise belief it's zero
that is actually very much again like
regression testing like if you're gonna
if you have um
if you're testing for for the effect of
a given
um Factor on height
that is related to the p-value you get
for height
is related to the model that includes
height and the model that doesn't
include height
and then
their sum of squares is compared
within the appropriate
statistical test family
t-test z-test f-score all giving you a
p-value
so this is very much like
statistics on regressions
one thing
maybe there there's a deeper reading
where this is clear but one way to talk
about parametric empirical Bays
is that like well first off it is it's
parametric
you're dealing with parameters so
sometimes that's not too helpful but the
empirical part
means like the way we're going to get
our D Matrix
are prior
is from the data
so like let's just say that we have
um we're measuring height in the
classroom
we might be able to use chapter 6 to
specify and furnish the model
but then
as soon as we make that first and then
we might set our prior would say well
let's have a super loose prior let's say
that it could be like
uniform across all you know
but of course who knows what the maximum
height is maybe it's not a human
classroom so we can't just specify a
uniform distribution
across
you know every finite value
and so a way to kind of break that
um a priori
challenge
where like you want your um prior to be
loose enough
to accommodate the full range of the
possible data
but also sharp enough so that you're not
just like starting like on like it's
just an absurdly uninformative prior all
priors are informative even a uniform
prior is still informative
the thing that matters is the strength
the weakness of the prior and the family
of the prior
so what you could do instead would be
you could measure
10 Heights or even one
and then use the mean and the variance
of that sample
empirically
to set your prior
so set just the mean of the prior on
height as the mean that you got from 10
and then you could just over disperse
the variance
so if there's somebody who's outside of
that bound
now it's like you know
you can be more confident but this is so
this is widely used
to take an empirical data set
and then use the data sets empirical
values and summary statistics to
parameterize the generative model
and then the ball goes from there
um and also the expectation maximization
algorithm
where you have a given data set and you
update the parameters in the generative
model and then you generate data
compatible with that model and continue
that is um very close to PEB
okay
9.5 instructions for model based
analysis
so let's copy these out
because the question was like how is
this
a figure 9.2 I guess section 9.5
and it's summarized in 9.2
here's the six steps
oh someone added a great
Okay so
this is a little bit of a review of the
textbook
but we're starting with data
collection
maybe the data already have been
collected
so we're putting aside the situation
where we're doing the meta modeling on
ourselves and then doing experimental
design and then collecting the data
we're just going to take it from the
data are collected
a pomdp
again discrete time in this case
is structurally prepared
according to the recipe in chapter six
pomdps
would we say are equivalent to
specifying a likelihood function
or they they embody or they entail a
likelihood function
what is the arrow between two and three
does merely constructing a pomdp in this
format
uniquely identify a likelihood function
or what what work has to happen right
here
just a thought we can you know learn
yeah
uh I don't think it uh these arrows
necessarily mean uh that
this particular component of uh the
modeling process necessarily uh
translates perfectly to the other stage
uh I think uh they're more likely to be
to show the dependencies among each
steps so uh in the case of the third
stage or the likelihood fun the
construction of the likelihood function
obviously it depends on what our pomdp
model uh the functions so I'm not sure
if we can I mean if it will I mean if
they were 100 isomorphic I guess they
would be redundant right
so yeah I think those arrows show
dependencies rather than translating
into each other
thanks I I
think I broadly agree
and there might also be some other ways
to draw it like the prior beliefs
is this Theta
I think this is using the uh figure nine
one ontology
this data is Big Theta
these are the experimenters parameters
the model
is the cognitive model of the entity
italic U tilde
is the observed data
so here's the observed data getting
passed
with pomdp and Associated likelihood
function
we can the likelihood okay the pmdp
describes variables in their
relationships
the likelihood function
allows us to create p
which is the distribution of
observed Behavior U tilde
conditioned upon
experimental parameters data
observations which are in this case the
ones that are provided to stimuli
experimental stimuli
and the model
then the parametric empirical Bays
comes in when we actually get the data
it comes in in six but we're getting
there we're on the path when we have the
data flowing from the experiment
we can then do the model inversion
rather than describing
the distribution of behavior that would
be generated by Theta o m
we're going to invert it
so we can talk about the distribution of
parameters experimental parameters
conditioned upon mou
Bayesian equation
allows us to have a proportionality
between what we really want to know
this Top Line
and
a
I don't know if I can call it a joint
distribution but these two multiplied
distributions
which is the probability of the param of
the experimental parameters given the
model
and separating out
the probability of U
H condition on all the rest
so this is leveraging the sparsity
of the inverted model
to facilitate a form
that is amenable to linear regression
type
equations this is like y equals MX plus
b
it's not
but it is this is like the same
structure
y m x plus b
but then these bars and their Associated
variances which come from a LaPlace
this is the p-value and the effect size
so for this third modality the effect
size is zero and the variance is you
know such and such
and then for this one we could say
the p-value or the base Factor
for this Factor mattering
it it's it's high the evidence for this
mattering is extremely high
so this is like If This Were a bar chart
and we're
um if we were in frequency statistics
land
and it were like 10 plus or minus 1.
then we we have a z-score of 10.
we're 10 standard deviations away from
zero so the p-value of the effect size
being greater than zero is
whatever it is for a p-value of a
z-score of 10. very low
but again this is like where the real
data collection
is going to be happening and interfacing
so now here's their description
collect behavioral data
formulate the pomdp
it takes parameters as input outputs are
fully specified but not yet solved pomdp
specify likelihood likelihood function
specify prior beliefs
often these will be centered on zero
with precisions reflecting plausible
ranges
that's interesting note
solve for posterior and model evidence
Newton is probably a reference there to
some gradient
derivative base gradient method I'm not
exactly sure
group level analysis
treating the estimated parameters for
each individual as if they were
generated by a second level model
this is exactly structurally
Anova
the group level analysis of variance
like
we had people throw the ball
there was type 1 and type 2 a person
and then the the weather type to is
there an effective type
you make two models one of them is a
model without type
one of them is a model with two
categories of type
then those two models
can be compared
in terms in the frequentest world
in terms of their hierarchical
likelihood
in the Bayesian World however a
limitation of the hierarchical
likelihood ratio test
is that the models must be strictly
structurally nested
they have to reflect direct
simplifications or elaborations of each
other
in contrast
Bayesian modeling allows us to use the
Bayes Factor
which can compare models that don't
need to be
strictly nested
so you could
test very structurally different
models against each other
it's kind of like information as a
common currency
in the Bayesian approach
it I I considered uh variable one two
and three
and then someone else could compare
variable four five six
and you can be like well how how good
are those two different models against
what we care about
in terms of informational Criterion AIC
Bic the base Factor
whereas if somebody said well I did
model uh with one two three and the
p-value is 0.01 and I did this with four
five six and the p-value was 0.01
those can't be directly compared because
the p-value is against like a local null
hypothesis and there's just like
probably other issues
so it's one huge advantage of the
Bayesian like
we're kind of we're past we're 50 years
past the Rubicon or 400 or whatever on
base but like
Bayesian formulations allow for the
generative recognition model the tale of
two densities
so you can specify something that
generates and recognizes data
that's one advantage another Advantage
is that you have access to all the
statistical tools
of frequentive statistics
and you can also
access this like informational
statistics
I'm sure there's like way way way more
rabbit holes there but like broadly
speaking
instead of taking experimental
observations in frequentism and then
mapping them onto a t distribution only
and then saying well now because of the
p-value
let me publish this paper
in the Bayes worlds
there are like richer comparisons and
like more nuanced penalization functions
of how many parameters versus how much
variance explains
you know just for example if anyone
thought bayesians were too confident or
if it wasn't the um
leading
modern strategy for dealing with
uncertainty
this design Matrix for a linear model
the SPM design matrices are like very
interesting looking
so the textbook has many many many
of these matrices they're encoded on a
grayscale
so like What's Happening Here
here are images through time each row is
an image
could be an image in a Time series could
be like different static images
here third column is time
so this is time point zero one two three
four five six times and then here's
condition one and two
first condition whether one is white and
black it doesn't matter
here
um condition let's just say Y is one
condition one was in effect
condition two is not and vice versa
but you could have overlapping
conditions
so it's like a graphical representation
and like this this is also common to see
this kind of like waterfall
here's
um patient one two three four five
Here's the the the four condition the
three conditions
in a randomized order
for the one two three four five patients
here's their um Global blood flow here's
some other measurements Etc
but it turns out with so this summarizes
the total design of the experiment
and it turns out like
you just
smash it like a matrix multiplication
like the design Matrix multiplied by the
observations
and one can imagine like if the
observations have no relationship with
the design Matrix
there's a null hypothesis that you could
get from random Matrix Theory
if the experimental design strongly
influences the observations
there's some informational outcome
96 in our final few minutes examples of
generative models
two experiments outlined in nine five
the details are not important oh
but it's too um isocating models
this is a continuous
time
left
tracking a moving Target
right
was a categorical eye tracking
as we've mentioned in this list like
doing some kind of a webcam
eye tracking cognitive model
would be massive
it's also very you know
sensitive technology I think
because it would be able to determine
somebody's cognitive model and their
attention in different ways
but
really be interesting
um
well it's going to say they they
actually already do that in specifically
for uh
like Championship like first person
shooter games
to try to catch people
uh using aimbots
like so they try to predict
you know where your eyes are going to be
based on the data in the game
and if you
are shooting you know or you're you're
acquiring the target faster than your
eyes uh you know the quiet could have
acquired the target then wow
yeah
well yeah interesting maybe even some of
the
um behaviors already
are out there so it's not like this is
yeah like maybe the data
already it's like that moving moving
Target one yeah yeah
and like
interpreting this as like an occupancy
density
but then having a cognitive model
where that is like an uncertainty
reduction or a salience
or relevance observation
which is implicitly what these usages
are
Disney trailers
um
models of false inference Julius Caesar
we had the Obama now we have the Caesar
um
discussion of phase optimality and
disorders
different pathological and neurodiverse
conditions addiction impulsivity
compulsivity delusions hallucinations
interpersonal personality disorders
ocular motor syndromes
pharmacotherapy prefrontal syndromes
visual neglect
disorders of enterocepted inference
so
if there's a parameters set that works
well
there's going to be
various parameter sets that exhibit
difference
outcomes
and then ask per Foucault Society is the
definer of Madness and all of that and
the DSM and
so you know asterisk asterisk asterisk
but broadly speaking these are models of
pathology
we outlined an approach that uses
theoretical models described in previous
chapters to pose questions to empirical
data
this lets us use active inference as a
non-invasive tool to probe the
computational processes that individuals
use to make decisions
so funny
well the model is not invasive
okay
I don't think any model is invasive
ultimately the six steps in figure 9.1
but it's not that's an error
it's figure 9.2
six steps in figure 9.2 provide a
generic method for Designing experiments
to non-invasively interrogate implicit
generative models people
or other systems used to drive Behavior
that's an opportunity to answer
questions about the function of the
nervous system in health and indices
all right
thank you fellows looking forward to the
conversation next week as well
thank you peace bye